Data. Everything we do today generates more of it. Whether it’s taking a ride in Uber or Lyft, adjusting the lights in your home with your Alexa, or sharing that family video on Facebook, we’re creating data at an accelerating rate every day. With that, 90% of the Internet has been created since 2016. But this isn’t a Big Data guide – it’s a guide focused on databases, one of the primary places where we have to put all the data that we’re generating.
Welcome to the 2017 DZone Guide to Databases. This year, we’ll take you on a guided tour looking at how to make your databases run aster, scale more easily, and more effectively secure the data that you store in them. At DZone.com, our Database Zone has been rowing steadily, fueled by a resurgence of interest in relational databases, the emergence of SQL layers on other types of data stores,  and the need to manage your databases like you manage the other parts of your infrastructure. This growth is driven largely by a convergence of database content with many of the different
other topics we cover. In this guide, you’ll find articles coverage
database + DevOps, database + security, database + cloud,
and database + agile.
Traditionally, changes to database technology have come
slowly compared to the other components of modern web
development. Businesses depend on databases to reliably
store their data – everything else, including ease of use, come
after that. Recently though, we’ve seen a relatively rapid
evolution of the database space as the need to handle larger
and ever-changing data has emerged. To be sure, the increase
in adoption of DevOps practices has also had a significant
impact on the pace at which databases and database
technology evolve. When you deploy daily or even weekly,
long gone are the days where you can wait for the DBA to
make adjustments to your tables or to settings on the server.
Today, you need to be able to apply changes to your database
through version control and integrate your database directly
into your CI and CD pipelines.
This move to DevOps is also driving the need to be more secure.
With more potential changes being made to the data, more
changes being deployed to the applications that leverage this
data, and more bad actors out there, database security needs
to be more flexible and offer a higher degree of comfort to the
teams responsible for the safety of your data. I believe that this is
a key area where we’ll see AI step in and prove its worth.
